Finding Aid for the Punk Zines and Ephemera Collection LSC.2276
UCLA Library Special Collections
Punk zines and ephemera collection
1977-2018
1983-1998
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2276
4.4 linear feet (5 boxes, 6 flat boxes)
The zines and ephemera assembled in this collection document the California punk music scene, primarily in the greater Los Angeles area, from 1977 to 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL AND AUDIO MATERIALS: Digital and audio materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection were acquired by gift and/or purchase from various sources. Source information, type, and date of acquisition are recorded with their associated materials in the finding aid.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9978158923606533
History
California punk rock quickly developed its own communities, sounds, and subgenres. Depending on the band or genre, influences can include surf rock, Mexican folk music, country, glam rock, East Coast punk, garage rock, and others. Punk communities often documented their subculture through zines. The zines focused mainly on the large Los Angeles and San Francisco scenes, but zines from smaller cities and towns also covered their local punk, rock, and underground music scenes. Zines were a primary way for fans to communicate before the Internet, and some zine creators switched to websites and blogs with the rise of online communities.
Scope and Content
This collection gathers zines and other ephemera documenting the California punk music scene, primarily in the greater Los Angeles area from 1977-2018. The zines vary in size, length, and medium; some are on newsprint, some are photocopied, and others are on gloss paper. The zines' content includes reviews, interviews, event announcements, news, letters, and creative works by the zines' creators and readers. The collection also includes a small amount of show flyers for performances in and around Los Angeles along with memorabilia donated to the Library Special Collections punk collective. A 2014 accrual is comprised of ephemera from Exene Cervenka, singer for the punk band X.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Zines, 1977-2016
Series 2: Show flyers and memorabilia, 1980s-2018
Series 3: Exene Cervenka materials, 1977-2008
Fanzines.; Punk culture -- California -- 20th century; Zines; Punk rock musicians; Punk rock music; Cervenka, Exene -- Archives
- Series 1: Zines, 1977-2016
  Scope and Content
  This series contains single issues and complete runs of punk rock zines, primarily with a focus on Los Angeles.
  Organization and Arrangement
  Zines are arranged alphabetically by title. Issues are arranged chronologically.
  - 60 Miles North, 1983-1985
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Purchased from Arthur Fournier fine & rare, Brooklyn, NY, 2015.
    Biographical/Historical note
    60 Miles North began in 1983 as promotional flyer made by Mike Rogers, a singer for the band the Desotos, which was headlining a concert in Camarillo, CA. Rogers and his bandmate Jeff Hughart expanded the flyer into a zine about the Ventura County and Santa Barbara County punk scenes due to popular demand. The zine's name represents Ventura's location relative to Los Angeles (60 miles north). Production of the zine continued for two years.
    Source:
    "60 Miles North -- Fanzine from the 80's!" 60 Miles North -- Fanzine from the 80's! Accessed March 08, 2016. http://www.60milesnorth.com/what.html.
    Scope and Contents note
    The zines in this subseries focus on the southern and central California rock and punk music scenes from 1983 to 1985. The content includes interviews; jokes; cartoons; album, concert, and film reviews and announcements; letters to the editor; and advertisements. These issues comprise 60 Miles North's entire run.
    - Vol. 1 No. 1 "LA Band Dance Nite", 1983 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 2 "Youth Camp Interview", 1983 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 3 "Halloween Issue", 1983 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 4 "Thanksgiving Special", 1983 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 5 "the day after...", 1983 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 6 "Big Bro' is Watching YOU", 1984 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 7 "Aggression Interview", 1984 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 8 "Stalag 13 Interview", 1984 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 9 "Interview with Ill Repute", 1984 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 10 "Dr. Know Interview", 1984 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 11 "Cirith Ungol Interview", 1984 July 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vol. 1 No. 12 "Anniversary Issue", 1984 September 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vol. 2 No. 1 "Halloween Horrors", 1984 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vol. 2 No. 2 "Holidayz Issue, Blasters Interview", 1984 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vol. 2 No. 3 "Too Much Tension? Get a Safe & Sane Lobotomy! Quick-easy-fast", 1985 January-1985 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vol. 2 No. 4 "Spring Offensive Issue! The Home Front", 1985 March-1985 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Better Youth Organization, circa 1981
    Purchased from The Book Shop, Covina, CA, 2015.
    Better Youth Organization was founded in 1979 by Shawn and Mark Stern, members of the band Youth Brigade, in response to exploitation, police violence, and negative attitudes toward the punk and alternative music scenes in Los Angeles. It eventually developed into a record label, which released its first LP in the early 1980s.
    "About BYO Records." Punknews.org. Accessed March 08, 2016. https://www.punknews.org/labels/byo.
    This subseries consists of a single preview for a forthcoming Los Angeles alternative, punk, and skinhead organization and zine. The content includes illustrations complementing the text, which expresses anger regarding unfair practices and police violence against the Los Angeles punk and alternative scenes, and calls for a new music industry that would not involve these practices. The preview also includes a call for letters and subscriptions to the zine.
    - Better Youth Organization, circa 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fix My Head, 2011-2015
    Gift of The Book Shop, Covina, CA, 2016.
    Fix My Head is a left-leaning, DIY, non-profit punk zine that is published by Portland, Oregon's Anna Vo. It is a People-Of-Color (POC) focused publication that interviews artists, academics, and activists about different struggles, with content predominately by women and queer folk. The collection contains issues 1-7 of the 10 issue run (as of 2019).
    "Zines." anna vo. Accessed June 6, 2016. https://annavo.wordpress.com/zines.
    - Issues 1 and 2: Activism and Feminism in HC, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Issue 3: Punx of Colour, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Issue 4: More Punks of Colour, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Issue 5: Radical POC, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Issue 6: QTPOC Punk Artists, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Issue 7: Geography, Identity and Diaspora, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ink Disease, 1984-1988
    Ink Diseas e was founded by Rachel Siegel, Antonio Lopez and Ivan Morley in the early 1980s, and continued into the 1990s. Thomas Siegel and Steve Alper joined the staff later, and remained with the zine until publication ended. The zine was initially an eclectic collection of interviews, clippings, photos, cartoons, and other materials, but became more focused in layout and content as its popularity rose. Its publication grew sporadically in the 1990s and eventually ended.
    "Ink Disease." ZineWiki. Accessed March 08, 2016. http://zinewiki.com/Ink_Disease.
    The three zines in this subseries focus on the Los Angeles punk scene in the 1980s. The content includes interviews, reviews, letters to the editor, editorials, opinion articles, cartoons, advertisements, and poetry. These issues cover only a small part of Ink Disease's full publication run.
    - Issue #8 "Interviews with: M.I.A., Minutemen, Butthole Surfers, Die Kreuzen, 7 Seconds, Mentors, Hirax", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Issue #10 "Goodbye D. Boon, Interviews with: Ian MacKaye, FlipSide, S.N.F.U, Great Plains, Agnostic Front, The Dead Milkmen", 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Issue #14 "Angry Samoans, The Beatnigs, The Dickies, Naked Raygun, No Means No, Savage Republic, Screaming Trees", 1988 Fall (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - I Wanna Be Your Dog, 1977
    I Wanna Be Your Dog was founded by Philippe Mogane, cofounder of Los Angeles record label Siamese Records, in the 1970s. It was published in both France and the United States.
    Leonard, Craig. "Artpedia." Gift for the Screamers. August 13, 2007. Accessed March 08, 2016. http://giftforthescreamers.blogspot.com/2007/08/artipedia.html.
    This subseries consists of a single zine, which was published by the American arm (based in Los Angeles) of an American-French punk and new wave zine. It comprises one issue out of I Wanna Be Your Dog's run. The contents focus on the Los Angeles punk music scene, and include reviews, interviews, song lyrics, editorials, advertisements, music news, fiction, and information on other zines and fan clubs.
    - No. 7 "Eddie Money", 1977 November (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - I Was a Teenage Filipino Skinhead, 2015
    Gift of Angel Diaz, 2018.
    These zines are both written and illustrated by Hepcat drummer Greg Narvas. The zines depict Narvas on his teenage journey of identity and non-conformity in the 1980s Los Angeles mod/ska/skinhead underground scene. They show his transformation from a Nu-Waver to a Mod, eventually evolving to a Skinhead.
    These zines were originally published in 2007, but the ones in the subseries were published in 2015 during their second print run. The collection contains 3 issues of the 10 issue run (as of 2019).
    - Volume 1: Where It All Began!, 2015 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Volume 2: A First at Fender's!, 2015 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Volume 3: The Modern Mayhem!, 2015 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The L.A. Beat, 1978
    Gift of Boo-Hooray, New York, NY, 2016.
    L.A. Beat was edited and published by Stephen Zepeda in Long Beach, CA. Zepeda also ran independent record label Beat Records from 1978-1980. Collection contains issue #2 featuring John's Children, The Jam, and Gary Valentine.
    - Issue 2: Superfluous Polka-Dot Issue, 1978 July (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Maximum Rocknroll, 1984-1997
    Biographical / Historical
    San Francisco's Maximum Rocknroll (MRR) is one of the longest running punk zines. It began in 1977 as a punk radio show on KPFA in Berkeley, hosted by Tom Yohannan and Jeff Bale, and became a zine in 1982. Tim Yohannan was the main force behind MRR until his death from cancer in 1998. MRR published its last print issue (#432) in May 2019.
    The 29 issues included in the collection span 1984-1997, with gaps, and contain local, national, and international content. MRR includes scene reports, articles, columns, and record, zine, and book reviews, and is especially known for practicing and promoting Do It Yourself (DIY) ethics.
    - MRR: No. 17, 19, 20, 25, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - MRR: No. 28, 29, 33, 37, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - MRR: No. 39, 84, 85, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - MRR: No. 86, 87, 110, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - MRR: No. 111, 112, 115, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - MRR: No. 116, 119, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - MRR: No. 133, 134, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - MRR: No. 136, 138, 139, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - MRR: No. 140, 144, 145, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - MRR: No. 155, 166, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - NO MAG, 1982
    Gift of Todd Grappone, 2015.
    No Mag was a Los Angeles punk and art zine published by Bruce Kalberg from 1978-1985. Collection contains one issue of the 14 issue run.
    - No. 9: Pop Trash Noise Music Nancy Reagan, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Paranoia, 1982
    Gift of Laguna College of Art + Design, 2017.
    Paranoia was a Reno, NV punk rock fanzine published in 1982 by Bessie Oakley and Jone Stebbins. They called it "the zine for blind and illiterate punks." Their main aim was to interview punk rock bands and ask them challenging questions, rather than adhering to the usual interview rules. Collection contains issue #5.
    "The Wrong Side of Reno: Three Decades of Punk and Hardcore in the Biggest Little City." Jeanne Jo, Mac Shopen. Accessed July 6, 2017.
    - No. 5: Minor Threat, Redd Kross, Husker Du, Chron Gen, T.S.O.L., 1982 October (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Punx Not Dead, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Gift of Megan Fraser, 2016.
    3.5 x 5 inch illustrated zine by Vivian Shih, Los Angeles, CA. This appears to be a single issue zine.
  - The Rise and the Fall of the Harbor Area, 2007
    Gift of The Book Shop, Covina, CA, 2015.
    The Rise and the Fall was a San Pedro-based zine focused on music, skateboarding, and art. It was started by Craig Ibarra and the local punk community in 2004 and lasted until 2009. Collection contains one issue of the 14 issue run.
    - No. 9: "Shawn Kerri, Keith Morris", 2007 January-April (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - SFTG, circa 1986- circa 1988
    Purchased from Arthur Fournier fine & rare, Brooklyn, NY, 2014.
    Kirk Dominguez and classmate Stephanie printed issues of SFTG in a Regional Occupational Program class in Cypress, CA in the late 1980s.
    O'Mahony, Dan. "Billy Rubin – Half Off / Haywire." Double Cross. March 21, 2010. Accessed March 8, 2016. http://doublecrossxx.com/archives-3/archives-more-older-posts-19/.
    The zines in this subseries focus on underground music in Southern California and comprise SFTG's entire publication run. The contents include interviews, art, photos, stories, and poetry.
    - No. 1 "Dead Kennedys (Jello), The Choice, Goldenvoice (Gary T.), Flipside (Al & Hud), Pig Children, Conflict (Colin), Plain Wrap", circa 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 2 "LA's Wasted Youth, DOA, Aggression", 1986 June (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 3 "Interviews with: Tony (Adolescents), The Establishment, Faded Glory, Dave (MDC), The Undead, Phantasm, Blast", 1986 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 4 "Ink Disease, Rik L Rik, SSD", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - No. 5 "Faith No More, Saint Vitus, Plasmatics, Mission, Misfits, Blondie", circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - No. 6 "Number Six is Free.", circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Stick Time, 2016
    Gift of Arthur Fournier fine & rare, Brooklyn, NY, 2016.
    Conceived of by Casey Cola, Brian and Nikki Tucker, and others in 1981 but never released. This edition was issued in conjunction with the exhibition FER YOUz: The Los Angeles Hardcore Years, 1980-1985 at Printed Matter's LA Art Book Fair 2016 at the Geffen Contemporary at MOCA. First printing of 250 copies.
    - No. 1: Interviews: Cops, Animal, Joe Blow, Lucky, Fear, Andy, 2016 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Superdope, 1991- 1998
    Superdope was founded by Jay Hinman in 1991, and ended publication in 1998. Hinman published the first seven issues in San Francisco, and the last issue in Seattle. After Superdope ended, Hinman went on to create a series of blogs about music and other topics.
    "Superdope." ZineWiki. Accessed March 08, 2016. http://zinewiki.com/Superdope.
    The zines in this series focus on independent rock music in the 1990s, particularly the San Francisco and Bay Area music scenes. The contents include reviews, interviews, music history articles and retrospectives, music news, contact information for record labels, and advertisements. The publication dates grew farther apart as time passed. They comprise Superdope's entire publication run.
    - No. 1 "Claw Hammer, Sonic's Rendezvous Band, Flasheaters, Radio Birdman, Red Transistor, Chrome", 1991 March-1991 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - No. 2 "Radio Birdman, Rudolph Grey, Boys from Nowhere, Spike in Vain, Monster Magnet, Simply Saucer, Flipper, Prisonshake", 1991 June-1991 August (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - No. 3 "The Gories", circa 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - No. 4 "A Chat with Sweden's Meanest, Brainbombs, Clawhammer, Styrenes, Solger", circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - No. 5 "Fly Ashtray, Thomas Jefferson Slave Apartments, Nightkings", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - No. 6 "Come, Post-Gibson Bros Super Spectacular", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - No. 7 "Doo Rag, Virginia Dare", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - No. 8 "Forty-Five 45s that Moved Heaven and Earth", 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - We Got Power, 1982
    We Got Power was a Los Angeles punk rock fanzine published by David Markey and Jordan Schwartz from 1981-1983. Their audience mainly included the first-generation hardcore punk music community in Los Angeles. The text and photographs in the zine capture the early punk spirit of the native bands at the time. Collection contains Issue #4 out of the five issue run.
    "WE GOT POWER!: Hardcore Punk Scenes From 1980s Southern California, by David Markey and Jordan Schwartz." Bazillion Points. Accessed July 6, 2017. https://www.bazillionpoints.com/shop/we-got-power-hardcore-punk-scenes-from-1980s-southern-california-by-david-markey-and-jordan-schwartz/
    - No. 4: Black Flag, Dead Kennedys, Bad Religion, Minor Threat, BYO, Husker Du, Suicidal Tendencies, 1982 July (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Xicanx Brown Grrrl Growl, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    This zine, made by Joss Moguel, is about their experiences being brown, genderfluid, and a muxer in the Los Angeles/Southern California Hardcore scene. Moguel is part of a three-person collective in the Los Angeles area called Xicanx Crybaby. The other two members are Rocio Rodriguez-Magadan and Eddie Cortez.
    This appears to be a single issue zine.
- Series 2: Show flyers and memorabilia, 1980s-2018
  This series contains flyers, posters, and other ephemera related to the Southern California and Los Angeles punk scenes.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO AND DIGITAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Better Youth Organization promotional poster, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    14.5 x 14 inch poster featuring album artwork for the Someone Got Their Head Kicked In! compilation on BYO records (BYO 001).
  - Chuck Briggs photo album, 1980-1995 (Box 7)
    Purchased from the Book Shop, Covina, CA, 2017.
    This album contains 175 original color photographs of American punk rock guitarist Chuck Briggs (1960-2000) on stage as well as off stage. Briggs played with the U.S. Bombs, among other bands. The photographs date from the 1980s to the mid-1990s.
  - Ed Danky vinyl records, 2018 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    Gift of James Danky, 2019.
    Würm album produced by Chuck Dukowski, founding member of Black Flag and a founder of Würm.
    Two vinyl records featuring guitarist and vocalist Ed Danky (1953-1990).
    Würm Exhumed vinyl record (12-inch) compilation including out of print debut album Feast along with unreleased tracks and demos.
    Don't Blame Me (7-inch) by Reign of Terror, a re-release of the 1983 version.
  - Fer Youz, 2016 (Box 5)
    Facsimile edition of photo portfolio by Brian and Nikki Tucker which circulated amongst the punk and hardcore community in Los Angeles between 1981-1984.
  - Lovedolls Superstar: Fully Realized, 2006
    Gift of Jordan Schwartz, 2018.
    Scope and Contents
    DVD copy of Dave Markey's 2004 directors cut of the 1986 sequal to Desperate Teenage Lovedolls. Presented by We Got Power Films.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Punk U students' punk quilt, 2017 (Box 8)
    Gift of Jessica Schwartz, 2017.
    Contains quilt created by students enrolled in Professor Jessica Schwartz's Musicology seminar, Punk U at UCLA in Spring 2017.
  - Alan Sacks DVDs, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Gift of Alan Sacks, 2018.
    Contains DVD copies of the films Thrashin' (1986) written and produced by Sacks, and Du-beat-e-o (1984) directed by Sacks.
  - Show flyers, 1980s-1990s; Flyers are primarily 8.5 x 11 inches. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    30 flyers for punk performances in and around Los Angeles in the 1980s and 1990s. Includes flyers for shows with Suicidal Tendencies, The Gun Club, T.S.O.L., 45 Grave, Circle Jerks, The Weirdos, and The Plugz. Venues include The Whisky A Go Go, The Starwood, and the Lhasa Club.
  - X Under the Big Black Sun tour pin, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Youth Party flyers, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Materials dontated to the punk archive from Paul Picasso to Sharon Farb, 2019.
    Flyers document performances by bands such as Castration Squad, Adolescents, Mau Mau's, U.X.A., Red Cross, The Brat, the Go-Go's, and the Germs at venues including the Vex, Hong Kong Cafe, King's Palace, Hotel Roosevelt, Lilo's, Lazaro's Ballroom, Starwood, Leonardo's Ballroom and the Masque.
- Series 3: Exene Cervenka materials, 1977-2008
  Purchased from Exene Cervenka estate sale, 2014.
  This series contains ephemera, publications, posters, recordings, and artwork from an estate sale held by Exene Cervenka, a poet, musician, and artist best known as the singer for the punk band X. Several items are autographed.
  - Rude Hieroglyphs, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    CD of the 1995 album by Lydia Lunch and Exene Cervenka.
  - Creem, 1978 April-1986 March (Box 9, Folder 2)
    3 Magazines
  - NY Rocker, 1980 September (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - ZigZag, 1977 August-1978 December (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Single issues of magazines, 1980-1988 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Contains issues of 99th Floor, Deep Red, and Trouser Press.
  - Monographs by Exene, 1993-2002 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Contains Virtual Unrealit y and A Beer on Every Page.
  - Autographed Exene setlist, circa 1990 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Family Torn artwork, 2008 (Box 11)
    Original framed collage. Back is signed by Exene.
  - Promotional materials, 1983-1997 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Contains a John Doe postcard, X Anthology booklet, and Beyond Baroque flier.
  - Show posters, circa 1990s (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Contains 3 posters for An Acoustic Evening with X and Jill Sobule, The Knitters, and Exene with Dexter Romweber Duo and Anna Kramer & The Lost Cause.